A Guide to the Croy Family Papers 1859-1938
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Croy Family Papers 1859-1938
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Ms2001-018
2 containers; 0.5 cu. ft.
Papers of the Croy and related families (especially the Dawson and Pepper families) of Montgomery County, Virginia. Includes correspondence, financial records, diaries, artifacts and photographs.
Dealer
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open to research.
Alternative Form
The Special Collections Imagebase contains digital images of each photograph and selected other items in the collection.
Biographical/Historical Information
Wilbur Alexander Croy, son of Andrew Jackson Croy, worked as a carpenter and house painter in the Blacksburg area. In 1901, Croy married Ellen Pauline (Ella) Dawson (1863-1938), the daughter of William and Rose Ann (Roseanna) Croy Dawson. The couple lived on the corner of Blacksburg's Roanoke and Wharton streets and had one child, Georgia (1902-2000). Ella's sister, Mary Dawson, married John Pepper, of Elliston, Virginia, in 1879.
For more on the Croy and related families, see 1889 Diary of Rosanna Croy Dawson, Blacksburg, Va.(F234.B5 D25 1972 Spec/Genealogy); 1890 Diary(F234.B5 D26 1979 Spec/Large); The Year of 1893 in the Life of Rosanna Croy Dawson of Blacksburg, Virginia(F234.B5 D28 1980 Spec/Large); and Blacksburg in 1898(F234.B5 D3 Spec/Large). Selections from the diaries, together with other information on the family, may be found on the Blacksburg bicentennial page.
Scope and Content Information
This collection contains the papers of the Croy family of Blacksburg, Virginia, together with materials from other related families in Montgomery County--particularly the Dawson and Pepper families.
The collection includes a small selection of correspondence and greeting cards, largely addressed to either Ella Dawson Croy or her daughter Georgia, together with a few of the family's financial records (tax receipts, account statements, etc.).
The collection also contains six diaries kept by Mary Croy Pepper from 1900 to 1904. The diary entries concern day-to-day activities in Roanoke, weather conditions, family and friends, and accounts of extended trips to Washington D.C. and the Virginia coast.
Among the small set of period artifacts in the collection are a pair of spectacles, a straight razor, baby shoes and a cigar box.
Perhaps most significantly, the collection holds more than one hundred family photographs--mostly unidentified--dating from the late nineteenth to early twentieth centuries and including a number of tintypes and cartes-de-visite. Represented in the photographs are works by a number of Southwest Virginia studio photographers, including C. A. Pugh (Blacksburg); Jewell (Christiansburg); G. N. Wertz (Abingdon); and Carbon, W. E. Eutsler, Kidd, H. V. Lineback, and W. C. Woolwine (Roanoke). Among the photos of scenery are images of Lovers' Lane on the Virginia Tech campus, P. Metzger's harness shop (in Blacksburg?) and Balanced Rock at Garden of the Gods, Colorado.
The collection also contains such disparate general materials as a handwritten poem entitled "Farewell," genealogical notes on the Dawson and Croy families, an IOOF membership certificate for Harvey Black, and a small oil painting (believed to portray the house at the corner of Roanoke and Wharton streets and possibly painted by Robert M. Dawson).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by material type.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
In 2015, a CD of Croy, Dawson, and related family photographs was donated to Special Collections. These images are ONLY available in digital format. They can be viewed online: http://digitalsc.lib.vt.edu/CroyFamilyPhotographs
Index Terms
Family Names:
Croy family, Blacksburg, Va.
Subjects:
Blacksburg (Va.); Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Montgomery County (Va.)
Contents List
- Correspondence and greeting cards 1896-1938 (Box-folder 1-1)
- Financial records 1920-1937 (Box-folder 1-2)
- Mary Croy Pepper diaries 1900-1904
  - Sep 1900-Jul 1902 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Jan-May 1903 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - May-Sep 1903 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Sep 1903-Mar 1904 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Mar-Jul 1904 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Jul-Aug 1904 (Box-folder 1-8)
- Artifacts n.d. (Box-folder 1-9)
- Photographs 1876-1903
  - A-C (Box-folder 2-1)
    - Callie Angell
    - John Angell
    - Susan V. Argabright
    - Earnest Barkman
    - Martha Brown
    - Andrew Croy
    - Mae Croy
    - Olive J. and Lelia J. Croy
    - Sarah Croy
  - D (Box-folder 2-2)
    - Byron W. Dawson
    - Carrie Dawson
    - Charles Wesley Dawson
    - Eva Dawson
    - Estelle Dawson
    - Lillie Dawson
    - [Warey?] Dawson
    - Willie Dawson
  - E-Z (Box-folder 2-3)
    - Florence Gray
    - Mary Virginia Gray
    - Walter Gray
    - Rev. Groseclose [David Bittle Groseclose?]
    - Christenia Harris
    - Jessie Read McCrea
    - Tully Foster McCrea
    - John Oliver
    - Miss R. H. Peck
    - A. P. Scanland
    - [Flora Stone?]
    - Alice Conway Tams
    - Lewis C. Winans
  - First-name-only identification (Box-folder 2-4)
  - Unidentified (Box-folder 2-5 (7 folders))
  - Scenery and other subject matter (Box-folder 2-6)
- General materials 1859-1938 (Box-folder 2-7)